Welcome back!
So far, we’ve explored what Enterprise Risk Management is, how
Internal Audit fits into the ‘Three Lines of Defense,’ and the
essential components that make an ERM framework effective.
In this module, we’ll shift our focus outward—to understand the
evolving risk landscape that organizations must navigate today.
We’ll examine the key global risk drivers shaping modern business
environments and unpack how risks can be categorized to support
clearer analysis and decision-making.
"The sources emphasize that uncertainty and risks are 'here to stay.'
In fact, they are a constant feature of the modern business
landscape. The ability of leaders to be agile in navigating this
uncertainty significantly increases an organization's capacity to
'pivot when the unexpected occurs,' allowing them
to adapt and survive.
The sources highlight several key global risk drivers that are
shaping the environment organizations operate in today:
Cultural shifts in workforce and society: This includes evolving
employee expectations, societal values, and demographic changes that
impact talent, operations, and reputation.
Lynn Fountain also speaks to the importance of people and culture,
recognizing them as top priorities for Boards and Executives.
She also highlights how staffing models and team dynamics are
impacted by organizational culture and employee turnover.
Sustained inflation and high interest rates: These macroeconomic
factors can severely restrict growth opportunities, impact profit
margins, and necessitate new financial skills within an organization.
Geopolitical risks and regulations: Global political instability,
trade wars, and an ever-increasing complex web of regulations can
significantly affect business operations, supply
chains, and market access.
Fountain frequently discusses the impact of regulatory changes,
especially Sarbanes-Oxley, on internal audit
functions and the need for compliance.
This reinforces the significant impact regulations have.
Technology innovation: While offering immense opportunities, rapid
technological advancements also bring risks related to adoption,
integration, ethical implications, and the need for new skills.
Supply chain disruptions: Global events, natural disasters, or
geopolitical tensions can severely impact supply chains, leading to
production delays, increased costs, and inability
to meet customer demands.
Employee attrition and layoffs: High turnover rates and workforce
reductions can impact productivity, morale, institutional knowledge,
and the ability to execute strategy.
This ties directly into Fountain's emphasis on talent acquisition,
development, and retention, which she identifies as a significant
challenge for internal audit teams and organizations broadly..
In summary, today’s organizations operate in an environment where
uncertainty is constant and global risk drivers—from cultural shifts
and inflation to geopolitical tensions, technology disruption, and
talent challenges—are shaping daily realities.
For leaders and teams, recognizing these drivers is essential to
build agility and resilience.